And then we had a meeting with the
editors
and we had to eat a little bit
and we got stuck in an
elevator,
for real.
[Music]
So sorry we're late, but
we'll go a little later anyway.
The purpose of this conference
is to talk about finding
that thing you love in your life.
What is it that you still haven't found?
What you would love to do with your life.
We see people who love what they do.
In Carola's son's room I saw
many YouTube photos of the band
.   I
once met Bono in Ireland.
Bono loves doing what he does.   It's
so nice to meet someone who
loves what they do.
In this conference, we're talking about
how to find what we love to
do.
And this thing that you love to do should
also be something that helps everyone
, all of
us
deeply, sorry, all of
us in the deepest part of our
hearts
who would want both things.
I would like to find someone like Bono
who found what he loves to do
and at the same time wanted to help the
world
and find peace within myself.
Are these three things possible?
So this is the purpose of this
talk.
Yesterday we talked about a new way,
[Music]
a new way to find
your life's mission.
Why were you born into this world?   Every
person's life
has a mission.   Every
has a purpose.
We should try to find out what
our mission is while
we are still young.
There is a purpose for which you came here,
and you can discover it.
Last night we started talking about this
system,
the diamond cutter system.
This is level two.
In level one
we learned how to make money,
we learned how to use the
diamond cutter system to make money.
At level two, which is this level,
we use the same system
to find our mission in this life.
What were we supposed to do
with this life?
Yesterday we said there are four steps.
in this new system.
Step number one,
we took two steps last night, remember?
And today we're going to do the other two.
Last night.
Step one.
What do you want?
You have to put together a short sentence.   I
told my friend, "I can achieve anything you
want.
I hope you can tell me in one sentence.
I want a million dollars,
and I want a girlfriend,
and I want a good
yoga practice.
And then I said, 'Okay, that's enough
for one short sentence.
Tell me what you want.'
So, tonight
I want to find my purpose in
life.
I want to find something I'm
good at that will also
help everyone else
. I want that.
That's step one. Decide what you
want. I
'm not forcing you.
If you want something else, that's okay.
There are people who say, 'I don't care what
my mission in life is.'"  What I do
want is a good girlfriend.
Some people are very intelligent; I do
n't want a girlfriend,
a jaguar, a car,
and then the girlfriend will come.
So I decided one thing,
but my suggestion is,
I want to find my purpose in my
life.
Step number two
is what Carola did last night,
meditation.
In step number two, you have two
tasks.
You're making a plan about two things.
You have to plant your seed in another
person.
You can plant whatever you want.  I want a
million dollars.  Plantal.
Then relax.  He's going to come to you.
I want a girlfriend.
Sow the bride and she will come.  Nothing
will be able to stop her.  She's coming.
I want my purpose in life.
So, plant it.
How to plant the seeds of your life's purpose?
You must plant it in another person.
How do I plant it in another person?
We did the meditation last night.
They close their eyes
and think of all my family
and all my friends.
Who doesn't know what to do with their life?
Some of my people came up to me and
said, "I don't know anyone like that."
And I told them, "Check for a day,
see if there's anyone like that."  Then I
came back and you told me.
The next day they came, I
found 100 people like that.   You did
n't look before.   We do
n't care about other people.
We just comb our hair.   We
never comb other people's hair.
This means that we are constantly
thinking about ourselves.
If I tell you, find a friend who doesn't
know what to do with his life.
People would say, I don't know anyone like that.
And I'm telling you, check it out, look, search for
two days.
Well, I found Mini,
a gentleman in Detroit
returned after two days.
I found the perfect person.
Son is poor,
has no partner,
is sick,
and they don't know what to do.
With just one person I can plant
four seeds.
Maybe you can find someone like that
in this system.   You
do step number two at home.
[Music]
Meditation doesn't have to be like this.
Think about
who I know in my family or my
friends
who don't know what to do with their lives.
So, think of someone like that.
Think of someone now.  Now
think of someone you know in a
minute.   He does
n't know what to do with his life.   He
is always searching and never finds.
That's all.  That's step two.
Then they start a plan for that person.
I'm going to take it to the cafe, for
example, tomorrow
and I'm going to talk to them, I'm
going to talk to them, I'm going to help them.
This is step number two, the slide you
see there, the photo.   I
suggest you go to the beach
and think,
who is confused about their
life?  Who can I help?   I'm
going to take them to the little cafe.   I
suggest you go to Starbucks.   It
helps the American economy.
Let's talk about Starbucks.
Sometimes I call it the four steps of
Starbucks.
Step number two in your mind, on the
beach.
Tomorrow I'm
going to take my friend to the Starbucks coffee shop
.   I'm
going to talk to him, I'm
going to give him some suggestions.
Perhaps I can suggest a website where
you can find a job.   Maybe
I know someone who has
a business, a company.
Think of suggestions for what to give her
at the beach.
You can sow many seeds
before doing anything.   He
is sowing seeds.  This is a
secret.
Most people don't understand
this.
They think that simply taking action
sows the seed.
But thinking sows seeds.
[Music]
Thinking sows more seeds than
doing.
So plan who you're going to help.   We
finished that last night.
We are now at step three.
This is step three.
Talk to them,
take them to Starbucks.  That's all.  That
's step three.   You have to
do it in the little cafe.
Never think,
oh, I don't know what to do with my life.
We focus on ourselves
and are always worried about
ourselves.
In this system,
when you have a big problem,
you have to help another person who
has the same problem;
this is necessary, you must do it.  You have no
choice.
Otherwise the system won't work.
The following year you'll come to me
and I'll ask you, "Did you achieve your
dreams?"  Did you fulfill your dreams?
And you're going to do this to me.
Starbucks.
So I know you didn't go to Starbucks
and I'm not going to talk to you about it again.
Starbucks.  Maybe I'll tell you Starbucks.
See you next year.
The next time I see you, I'm going to tell you
Starbucks.  And you have to say yes to me.   I
'm serious.
It's very simple.
If you didn't go to Starbucks, you did
n't help someone else.
If you don't help someone else, you ca
n't plant the seed
and your life will be the same as it is now.  It's not going
to change.
The measure.
[Music]
Of course, the thermometer with which we see if
you sowed seeds or not, that you are
changing your life.
In China they don't say shimbaco.
Starbucks.  Starbucks.   They
call Starbucks shimbaco.
So they have to do shimbaco.
That's step three.
Step four.
Last year I told you about step number
four.   I do
n't have to tell you all of them again
.
One night I returned from work,
went to my lama,
I lived with my lama for 25 years.   I
went to my lama's room
and he said, "Did you do your meditation today?"
Oh, Lama, I'm so tired.
I have to get up at 5:30. I
spent two hours on the
bus to go to New York.
Then I took another two hours on the
bus back, and I'm a monk. I'm
not allowed to stay in the city. I
have to go back to the monastery.
It's about 9 at night, I'm so
tired.
And the lama asks me, "Did you do your
meditation?"
When am I going to meditate?
And he tells me, "You have to do it on the
sofa.
Sit there on the couch,
lie down on the couch.
In Tibet it's not allowed to lie down on
the couch
because your feet are very dirty."  And he
said to me, "Put your feet up on the sofa.
Think about what you did today.
Have some coffee.
That's very strange,
[Music]
because if I came in and
spilled a little coffee on the sofa, it would
hit me.
He has a rosary like this one
that he doesn't use to pray,
but to
hit me on the head.
I had red marks here on my forehead.
Everyone laughed at me because the marks
lasted two hours.
He has some coffee and says to me,
"Lie down,
think."
Think about what you did today.
Did you help anyone today?   Did
you do anything good today?
He told me a very strange story.
One day we received a phone call
from the Catholic Church in our
town,
saying that Pope Saint Paul had
made a John Paul, sorry, had made
an announcement.
All churches
have to invite people to
give lectures from other religions.
So, in the phone call, they were
inviting him to my lama's lama,
and I said to him, "Do you want to go?"  And then
he said, "Yes, I'm happy to go."
And I helped him translate
and we went to a big cathedral.
We met the priest, who was a very
good person,
and we had a nice conversation. He
said to me, "Well, come to the front of the
church,
a big cathedral."
So, we were walking down the
central aisle, the
three of us together,
and my lama stopped and asked the
priest, "
What is that little room over there?"
A priest went in,
sat down in the little room,
a woman came in
from the other side of the room through a
small door, and then they closed the door.
[Music] was playing there,
and the priest said, "No, no, it's nothing
bad, nothing bad."
She did something wrong, a bad
deed, and now she has to confess her
wrongdoing.
There's like a wall in the middle.
She can't see through this
wall to the other priest on the
other side
and has to tell him,
for example, what she did, like, for
example, I got angry with my husband yesterday.   So
what happens then?
Then the priest tells her, "Well, for
example, you say some Hail Marys,
like 35 Hail Marys,
and that's enough,
and she's clean. Confession, she's
clean.
My lama says, "Wow, that's a great
system."  Just like what we do
.  We do what we have,
this thing, this rosary.
Let's go to the monk,
I had a fight with my husband yesterday.
Okay, you have to make 35 mone.
It's the same thing, he said, that's a good
system.
Where is the other one?
The other one, what about her?   The
other little room.
Which little room?  The priest said.
[Music]
The person enters and the priest enters the
small room.
And what do you need two small rooms for?
They have to go into this little room and
tell the priest all the good things they
did.
And then the priest is going to say to him,
"Congratulations,
you're a very good person.
This is the confessional,
this is the rejoicing one.
You have to have two.
This is very serious in our system.
When you do something good,
you're planting a seed.
[Music]
You took your friend to Starbucks and
talked to him about his problem because your
friend doesn't know what to do with his life.
When you get back home,
[Music] you eat
, you eat dinner, you
clean up.
If there's no room left, I give you permission
to watch a little bit of
television.
So you watch television.
Then you get up, you go take a shower,
you put on your pajamas.
She's in the picture, she's giving us the
example.
This is meditation,
[Music]
a special meditation posture. You do
n't have to sit like this. It
's not necessary.
Why?
Because you're going to meditate on your knees
in this one. Your knees are going to hurt so much
that you're only going to think about that.
When you were  In high school, if you
had a boyfriend,
you'd think about him, that's how you thought about him.
Look up at the ceiling. I do
n't know why, but looking up
helps with concentration.
Oh, he was in my class today. He
said to me, "Good morning."
Maybe he'll ask me
out next week.  I like her hair
and your mom is yelling at you.
You cleaned, you washed the dishes.  Are you
ready to go to bed?
Maybe the week after
next week.
In Tibet they call it Nieepa.
[Music]
Meditation is so deep
that someone could put
McDonald's fries right in front of your
nose and you wouldn't smell them
because meditation is so good, so
deep.
Complete and total focus
on the groom.   You have to
do the coffee meditation [Music].  The focus of this
meditation is: I did a good thing.
I took the person to Starbucks, I
helped him figure out what he should
do with his life.
That was very smart.
This is how to sow seeds.
I did a good job, I made him
happy,
and I'm testing the new system.   I
'm not looking for a new job at the
newspaper.   I
'm not calling all of
my dad's contacts.
[Music]
I helped someone else find it.
Something's coming.
It's final.  That's what's going to happen, 100%
sure.
So now you know how to find
purpose in your life.  Four steps.   I
call it the four steps of Starbucks.
The next time I see you, I'm
going to ask you if you went to Starbucks or not
.
If you tell me no.
I have a guard.  Bouncer.   Bouncer
.
There's a bouncer who's going to kick you out
Um, it occurred to me tonight that some
of my teachers from the
TCI teachers,
we now have a very nice group of
teachers in Argentina
and we have a group of teachers who
came from other countries, are
going to help us tonight
and through the three-day
weekend retreat.
Uh, it costs us a lot of money to
bring you here, that's why
we're charging you
admission.
I think we're going to be successful in losing
money,
but we believe
the group at the retreat
should be very intimate and small.
So, a teacher
with small groups of people
so you can frankly and
openly say what your problem or your
dreams are.
and they can help you during these
three days.
So I'm going to ask them one by
one to come up and show tonight.
[Music]
First Ula who is from Germany.
I work to find jobs for other
people.
I work for a company that finds
jobs for other people.   I'm
working, helping the boss, the
manager who finds so many people working
that he gives me a small promotion,
and I'm very good at what I do.
I'm very good.  I have a lot of
perfect people that I bring.
I feel I have to do my own
work, my own business.
Yes, that would be a good thing, wouldn't it?
Yes. You're going to make a lot more money, a lot
more money.  Do your business.
No, no, no.  Forget it.  You already have a good
job.   It
guarantees you payment.
No, no, no, no.  Many people will
work for you.  They're going to do
everything.  You don't have to do anything.  Don't
forget, he can't do that.  You have
plenty of time,
6 to 12 months, to start your business.  Do you know
how many of his businesses are doing badly?  You are so
good.  It's going to be fantastic.  Everything is going to
be excellent.  Big money.
You forgot.  No, don't listen.  Don't listen.
You heard.  No, you kept your mouth shut.  I
told you to shut your mouth.
No, no, no.  What do I have to do?  I don't know
what I have to do.   Do
you want to kill this woman?  No, you
be quiet, you be quiet.  No, but what should I
do?
Ul, I have such a problem.
What do you think I should do?
What's your problem?   Should I stay
where I work or start my own
new company?  What do you think?
Let's go to Starbucks to get laid.  Let's
do it.
I would like to talk to you a little about
what would happen
if you learned this new system.
What is the old system?
50,000 years ago.
People didn't know how to
farm.
If you wanted rice,
you had to go to the forest, search,
try to find some rice.
Later,
someone had a very strange idea.
When you have rice,
don't eat it.
Throw it on the floor,
cover it with dirt,
wait three months and it will come.
I think the man who invented
agriculture
was smarter than Einstein.   We do
n't know his name,
but he invented agriculture.   That's why we're
eating;
we eat thanks to agriculture.
Try to imagine,
[Music]
is like such a big leap of
imagination.
You're like a caveman,
you have a little rice, you're hungry,
don't eat it.
Throw it on the floor, cover it.   It's
crazy.
I feel like that man
when I feel like that man when he
tried to explain to his friends what he
did.
I discovered something.  That?
When you have a little rice, don't eat it
.  As?
Throw it on the floor.
This club.
Come here and throw dirt on it.
After three months
you will have many rice plants.   You don't have to
go looking for rice anymore
.   You
can set up your cave and do the
coffee meditation.
The rice will grow on its own.
You don't understand how incredible that
moment was.
We are doing the same thing.
We're trying to talk to you,
we're trying to tell you something new
and it sounds crazy.
Today I saw a talk in a very large group
of business people.
There were 400 business men and women.
They asked me, Michael,
"What's your suggestion for building a
$250 million company?"
And I told them, pay extra taxes,
give 10% more than what you're supposed to
give to the government.
And they said to me, "Are you crazy?"  And I told him,
"No, you're crazy.
I work six months a year. You work
every day.
I make 200 million.
Prove it.
[Music]
When you pay your taxes, you're
helping 30 million people in
Argentina.
Every time someone drives their car,
they're driving, they're using that car
on a street.
I made that street.
I didn't make the potholes.
Oh, no, no. The potholes.
I don't pay for that,
but I'm paying for the street.
Every time someone drives on that street,
I have more seeds and I can make more
money.
At the end of the talk, they were very
happy.
In this system, you're not looking for things, you
simply sow them.
And then you relax.
I'm talking to them about a new way
to find purpose in their lives. It's
never too late for this. It does
n't matter how old you are.
If your degree is finished, your
business degree, for example, is finished,
and your children are grown, it
's not too late.
If you follow this system,
the new purpose will..."  It's coming to you.
A great purpose is coming to you that will make you
very happy
and will help the whole world. You
just have to plant it and then
relax.
So I'm
advertising
the new system. I
have seven reasons here to start the
new system.
The page is eight,
number one.
Your parents
don't have to search anymore. You're
not like a caveman anymore.
Just plant the seeds and
then relax.
Don't work so hard to find a
job, to work all day.
It's very frustrating for me.
Like trying to explain to a
caveman,
don't walk,
don't walk. Plant, plant. Relax,
relax. I
'm serious, I'm not
joking. I
came to Buenos Aires,
we were at my mom's house
and we saw people walking around, all
worried.
My heart feels sad.
Just plant.
Don't go looking for things.
Plant your boyfriend and then relax. He's going to
come, he's
going to pursue you, you wo
n't be able to avoid him.
Relax.
This is  A new system.
This is about the second, the
second point, bad.
These days your parents are constantly
nagging you.
Find a good job,
make money,
get out of the house,
you're 35.
Go, go. They're
always yelling at you.
If you plant, where?
[Music]
If you plant at Starbucks,
I promise you
your parents will shut their mouths
because you'll have a
fantastic job,
which makes a lot of money
and helps the world
and makes the noise parents make
stop.
That's benefit number two.
Number three,
sorry, this symbol is a symbol that
means I have to decide something,
I stay at my job
or I quit and start my own company.
If I stay, I get a check every
week, no problem.
If I quit,
I can start my own company,
maybe I can make more money than I do
now,
but then I have to pay all the
taxes,
right? But then you can, sure, you can
hire an accountant.
Yes,  But if I have to hire more
people, it's going to give me a headache because
people are always problems.
No, no. So, hire a
general manager,
you go to the beach,
and the general manager is going to argue with
the people.
But they're going to call me when I'm at the
beach in the middle of the night.
Oh no, we have a problem.
A client didn't pay. I'm
not going to be
thinking 24 hours a day about
all my problems.
In this system,
there are no more decisions to make.
Nothing,
no decisions at all. Do I have to
do this or do I have to do
that?
That's a bad question. The
performance you just saw was about
that.
The question is already bad. Do
you have to quit and start your own
company? That
's a bad question. There is
no answer. Why?
Because some people quit their
jobs, start their own companies, and
make a lot of money.
Some people quit their jobs,
start a company, and lose all
their family's money.
[Music]
Some people stay in their
jobs, reach 60, and don't make
any more money.
[Music]
Some  People stay in their
jobs, get promotion after
promotion, become vice presidents,
and get paid a lot of money.
Starting your own company
sometimes works,
sometimes it doesn't. That's
bad.
Staying in your job sometimes works,
sometimes it doesn't. That's bad.
Both decisions are bad. Why?
Because you don't know what's going to happen.
Maybe you'll succeed, maybe you'll fail.
Stop thinking like that.
That's
caveman thinking.
Plant the seed, relax.
[Music]
The decision is going to be made by you.
Someone is going to come to you.
I need to start a company. I
like you. Here
, take this. Start the
company,
you can be a partner or your boss. You
're doing great at your job.
Tomorrow you're a vice president.
Plant the seed and relax.
One of those two is going to happen to you
and it's going to be successful for you.
If you don't plant the seed,
you can try either one and they're
both going to fail.
No matter which path you take,
No matter what you do,
plant the seed and then you'll
succeed. Either way, you'll do
well. If you don't plant the
seed, you'll fail either
way. This is a new
system.
I like this. Plant the seed,
relax. You
don't have to be like Ula.
[Music] She
was sitting here in the middle,
fighting with her thoughts.
In the end,
she did the smartest thing, she
took it to Cecilia Starbucks,
planted the seed,
didn't make any decisions,
just planted the seed, stopped
making decisions, and go to Starbucks.
Starbucks. That's all you need,
and then relax.
No more doubting about what I have to
do.
I did the wrong thing,
I took the job,
but I'm not sure if I should have taken it
.
Maybe I don't like this company.
Maybe I could be making more
money at another company,
maybe I'm not in the
right job.
Decide what job you want to do.
For example, I want to do what I love,
but I don't know what
Go Starbucks,
help someone else find
what they love to do. Plant the seed and
then relax.
That makes your face age,
you get all those weird lines,
and if you make decisions,
but plant the seed and relax,
and your face will be like the Virgin
Mary's.
You're happy all the time, you
're not always doubting,
just plant and relax.
This is interesting.
This is interesting. The little
boy got a good ice cream.
If she weren't there, he would be
happy.
But she got an even better ice cream.
That makes him unhappy.
He's jealous
of the other person.
In this system,
generally when you're successful,
if you become rich, for example,
or you have a high position
somewhere,
you're like the girl.
Everyone is jealous of you,
they're kind of hoping you fail,
they want to put you in the newspaper. He
was very rich, but then he lost everything.
He had a very high position and now he's a
nobody.
Everyone really likes to read
about these things.  Why? Because
they're jealous.
In this system,
in this system, you have to help
the other person take your position.
If you want money, you have to help
other people make money.
When G. Michael walks in, then enters
a room, it's like, "
He made me rich.
He found me, he helped me find a
boyfriend."
[Music]
They're not jealous
because in this system,
to achieve what you want,
you have to help others
[Music],
and then everyone in your life
loves you
because you're helping everyone.
This is a system that works better.
Nobody's going to be jealous of you,
and then you're comfortable and you feel very
happy.
This system automatically gives you peace. You ca
n't avoid it.
To achieve anything you want,
you have to go
and make friends with someone else,
and everyone loves you.
Nobody's going to look at you like that,
and you're going to be successful,
and everyone is going to congratulate you and
be happy and support you in what you
do.
[Music]
Because in order for you to be  To be
successful, you must have made them successful
first.
It's a good, beautiful system. It's a
peaceful system where there is harmony.
[Music]
What's it called?
Go to Guadalajara, to Lake Chupala.
That's the lake, and relax.
Plant the seed and relax.
Don't make any more decisions.
Every time you have to make
a decision,
every time you want something,
the course of action to make that
decision is always the same:
Help someone else first achieve
what you want to achieve.
Jesus said, "Do unto others as you would have them do unto
you." So don't worry,
don't decide, "I have to do this, I have to
do that," just plant the
seed
and then relax.
All those decisions come to an end.
your life.  I can't describe to you how happy he's
going to be.
I travel all over the world,
to many, many countries.   I have
n't found anyone yet who is
happier than me.
I simply plant things and
then relax.
This system is so nice.   I do
n't want to see you next year with that
face.
I want to see you like this next year.
This is Christmas.   He's
looking for Santa Claus.   It
means to sow the seed.
Something beautiful will come back to you.
through the chimney
and then you can't even imagine it.
Don't even try to imagine it.
Sow the seed and enjoy it
because what comes back
is much greater than you can
imagine.  You can't imagine it.  Don't
try to imagine it if you don't want to.
Send the seed.
I never imagined it would be
300,000 diamonds per day.
I thought it was going to be one or two diamonds
per day.
If you had asked me back then, if
you were successful, how many diamonds would
you make per day?
I would say, I would have said three or
four,
300,000
every day.   I
never thought of something like that.
Sow the seeds
because they grow like crazy.
Something, and then something very beautiful that you can't
even imagine, is going to
come to you.
Sow, for example, the seed of the
bridegroom.
This is level four.  They'll have to
come back for level four.
So, the boy
is much more incredible than you
can imagine.  Honestly,
help someone else find their
passion
and that passion will come to you, and you can't
imagine what it's like.
But you can enjoy the wait,
sow the seed,
and after sowing the seed, you
immediately begin to enjoy.   You
don't have to wait for the seed to
grow to start enjoying it,
because it's going to be fantastic
just planting it
while you're waiting for it to
grow.
You can say, "Wow, this is going to be
amazing."
And you can start being happy
even before the seed sprouts,
because you can't even imagine what's
coming.
Last week we were in Cali.
I had never been to Cali in my entire
life.
People came to a conference.
The month before that, I was in Moscow.
When I was little,
Moscow was our enemy.
The people, the Russians, were our
enemies; they were all bad.
The first night in Russia, there were
between 800 and 900 people. They
all loved us.
We were so happy together.
I never would have imagined that in my
life. I never dreamed
that this would happen to me. I never
thought it would happen to me.
So just enjoy it,
plant the seed,
and then enjoy it.
Something wonderful is going to come back to you. There's
a meditation you can do.
[Music]
This meditation will help you have
more  Peace, it's
going to help you be happier.
A happy person understands these
things faster.
So let's do a meditation
beforehand. It's
not a Buddhist thing. You do
n't have to go and do it.
Anyone can do it.
I taught this meditation in the
Communist Party in China.
Everyone is doing this meditation,
and their work is going fantastically;
it's working.
It's like I'm giving them a little
treat, a
chocolate. Try it;
everything in your life is going to be happier.
I want to introduce you to our friend,
her name is Tiffany Sims.
Back straight,
eyes slightly closed,
face relaxed,
and bring your attention to your breath.
And begin to observe your
thoughts.
[Music]
In a few moments, we're going to vote on how many
thoughts we have about the future
and the past. You
don't try to control the mind;
just observe.
Now open your eyes
and raise your hand if most of your thoughts
were in the future.
In the past,
who was totally in the present?
Some.
Well, for the rest of us, we're going to go
back to meditation to learn
how to stay in the present.
So, closing your eyes,
again going back  Focus on your breath
and observe your thoughts.
Visualize a wall made of
translucent glass.
This wall is in front of your mind,
blocking all thoughts of the
future.
Now only thoughts
of the present and the past remain.
Visualize another glass wall
behind your mind,
blocking all thoughts of the
past.
Your mind
is now forced to be in the present.
Feel the relief
of being in the present
without expectations
and worries, the
relief of being here
in this room
with these people,
in your body,
with your breath.
Stay here for a few moments.
Gradually
deepen your breathing,
and when you're ready,
you can open your eyes.
Jump up there. That's it. Jump up there.
[Music]
Let's begin.
We're going to ask you to ask questions
in a little while.
If you don't give us a really good question,
I have some friends who have
questions prepared.
[Music]
It's okay if we do 15 or 20 minutes,
right? Let's leave 15 or 20 minutes
later.
If you have to go home, that's
fine, you can leave.
[Music]
I think we should be able to answer
seven questions.
Before we begin the questions,
I want to tell you about a project
called Caladanda Solidario.
Carola and Tomás are running it,
and they're helping children in the neighborhoods
by teaching them yoga,
teaching them how to live better lives.
We're planning for me to
participate in this program on my next visit.
I think it's a very good program.
If you'd like to help
them,
please talk to them after
this talk.
This is a great opportunity to
plant seeds.
This
teaching we had for two days
is a new idea;
it's like a philosophy,
but a philosophy without helping people with
your own hands
means nothing.
You have to learn this method,
and you have to help other people
with your own hands. This
will make you a
complete, whole, and whole person; it
will make you completely happy. You have to
do both.
With your mind, you have to understand;
with your hands, you have to help.
Many hands are like gold,
many mouths are like  Poison.
Paula Peralta,
Paula, Paula Peralta, please, if you
can stand up. Paula, there.
Paula Peralta is coordinating this
Caladanda Solidario program, so,
uh, if you can talk to her, if
you want to help in any way with the
program to teach yoga in the
underprivileged neighborhoods of Buenos Aires.
Yoga and how to plant seeds, all this
that we're talking about is also
taught to them.
Questions.
Ask me some questions and I can
rest and they answer. Let's
see, there's a question.
I want to know how I can help a
friend who is very, very sick and doesn't believe
in any of this.
[Music]
So that's a good question. It's a very
good question
and the answer for this type of
question is always going to be the same,
because where the pen comes from, it
comes from me.
So my friend is no
different from the pen.
If I see that my friend is sick,
where does what I see come from?
There are a couple of ways in which
you can approach this
problem.
Many times the  People ask us about
children,
for example, "How can I get my child to
practice this?"
And the answer is the same again.
Where does my child come from?
But another answer we can give is
what we call the unstoppable seed.
And the idea is if you can, like, do a
trick, do a trick for them so that they
plant the seed they need to
plant.
And Michael's example is that he had a
friend who was very stingy,
who didn't give extra money for anything.
And then he saw that this was
starting to cause problems for his friend.
So he took him to a restaurant
and said, "I'm going to pay."
And when the meal was over, "Did
you like the food?" "Yes, it was very
good.
I want to leave a big tip,
but I have to go to the bathroom."
And then he gave about $100
and said, "I'm going to give you the $100."
When the waiter comes, you give him the
$100."
Then he went to the bathroom.
So, while he's looking far away
,
around the...
and he sees when the waiter comes and when his
friend gives him the money
and comes back
and says, "Did you give the waiter his money?"
Yes,
the waiter was happy. Yes, he's very happy.
And then his friend felt very good
because he gave the money,
saw how happy that waiter was, it made him
feel good,
and he wants to do it again.
So, and he did a trick for him.
So, maybe you can also
think of some way you can do
this, a trick like that with your friend. You
don't have to explain seeds or
emptiness or any of these things. You
just trick them in some way
so they can help someone else.
But if you want that to work, what do
you have to do?
You're going to have to make sure that you
're taking care of people who are sick,
and you'd have to avoid doing things that
could hurt others.
Thank you very much.
[Music]
More  A very elaborate question like this
is, why are
n't we doing this course for
17- and 18-year-olds?
[Music]
My kids are there. If they want to come,
they can. Yes, the thing is, you have to
bring them.
[Music]
I have children.
I teach these things in Virginia, in the
United States,
and when I started teaching, I did
n't want any children there
because it interrupts the meditation,
and we are very
serious practitioners. Then I
thought, that's
crazy. There
are moms and dads here just like me.
I have a 14-year-old and a 10-year-old.
And then I thought, this is going to be a
lineage of families.
[Music]
So now the moms don't have to
find somewhere to leave their
kids to come to the talks.
They bring the kids to the class with one
condition:
the kids have to be quiet
when we meditate.
And something incredible happens:
the kids are very intelligent
and understand it much faster than
we do,
and all the adults
are stuck with these times and their
problems.
And this girl who has  About 15 of them
raise their hands
and respond wonderfully,
[Music]
but I think that I, as a teacher, and all of
us, should put more
emphasis on teaching young kids.
So thank you for planting the seed
in my mind.
And I'd like to
say that what we're doing at
Caladanda Solidario, the idea is precisely that, not to
start with kids even
younger than 16 or 17 years old, and right from the
start. Imagine if they told you this
right away, right? And well, now we're
working in underprivileged neighborhoods
teaching kids like that, but what if
we also went to all the schools?
Today at the previous conference,
a man approached me—you know, those
coincidences, you see there are no
coincidences—the seed sprouted,
a man came up to me and said, "I
love Gesicher's talk and I
have many contacts in schools and
peace, get ready," because he said, "I'm
going to help you so that we can start doing
these courses as mini-courses in all
the schools in Buenos Aires, because of the  At
least from the start, right?  Let it be like a
basic course, a basic course in all
the schools that invite us in Buenos
Aires, and this gentleman has the resources,
he has the contacts to do it.  So,
if you like the idea, you know, peace is back there
, you get together with peace and we
start doing something real
and I get to rest.
[Music]
One reason is that you don't plant it
The other reason is that you are impatient
and don't see, don't wait when it
blooms.
So, either you planted it with bad
technique or in bad soil, or you didn't give it
water and fertilizer.
Oh, you didn't wait long enough.  If
you plant a watermelon, no, it won't grow right away
.  You have to wait a while.
There are techniques.  What Gh Michael teaches us
in the retreats and in his courses
are the techniques so that instead of it
being a crop that
lasts, say, 6 months, you can make it
more hydroponic.  There are techniques to
do it faster.
And then there's something else: sometimes
you sow a seed and another one you had
previously sown blooms.
And he makes an analogy in his book that
Armic Management is going to have,
which is like airplanes that are about to
take off.  You plant a
seed and this seed has a
flowering date, a take-off date
to bloom in your consciousness.  in
your mind's phenomena, let's say,
uh, and the sowings, but well, it happens
that there were other previous ones that were there
waiting for their takeoff date and they are there
online.  So when you plant
one with a lot of passion, with a lot of power, it
may sometimes push the others
that were there before.  Then, and
a little confusion arises.  That's why it's
important to learn all
these topics about seeds very well and come to the
retreat.
[Music]
Hello, my name is Estela.
And I want to ask if my purpose is to
work for my country.  I am
very distressed by the situations we
are going through.
I understand that the emissions have to
be very large, or I don't know how to find
someone who has a purpose
to help another country; it's difficult for me.
Uh, when there are such big projects,
but I'm convinced that the
path is
[Music]
Hello, thank you, thank you for the question,
it's very nice.  Ah, the first thing we
have to understand is that from a
very small seed, which is only like that,
let's say, from a watermelon, for example, a
whole watermelon plant comes out after
a while, we don't know when, right?
After a while.  And from that plant there are
still many watermelons, a lot of
watermelons.  It means
that a small seed produces a
very large fruit, much larger than the
seed.  And inside each watermelon there
are even more seeds of the same kind, of
the same quality, right?  So, it's not
absolutely necessary to go to Peru and
change the Peruvian government to
help an entire nation. But the seed you're planting has to be just right.
The action is small, the result is
great.  So, if you find yourself
helping a lot of people with a
little bit of effort, or helping
someone who also wants to help many
more people—let's say, someone who
helps 100 or 108 people—
that's going to grow, and there will be many
people helping even more people.
So the motivation behind any action will
bear much fruit for you.
Hello, my name is Silvia.  Hi, my name is
Silvia.  My question is, I have a
priest who is a very good friend, he is a
very good person and he gives a lot to
people, but I look unhappy,
[Music]
this is obvious.  It's seen in many areas, isn't it?   It's like they see a
lot of people
doing good or being very
generous, but they don't see that they're rich,
right?  Or that you are helping others
but you don't see them being happy.  And
then here we can talk, for
example, one of the reasons we can
talk about is that it's
again, as Alejandro said before,
right?  It's like there's a technique to doing
these things, and if we don't do
them with technique, the results
are very mild, but they don't
have the power we
're expecting.  So, what
your friend is missing is the technique of
how to be happy, what he needs to cultivate
to be happy.  Um, for each of
these points, for example, the point
just mentioned about this lady,
right?, she was told, "Find a person
who is helping many people, you have to
choose who you are going to
help and how you are going to help them."  That's why
the person you choose is so important,
and then you develop the
technique, and once you develop
the technique it's like a ball that starts
rolling on its own.  What I would
say to a person like that is, well, they have to
wait, there's a gap, right?
As Alejandro said before, between
sowing the seed and receiving the
result, you also have to know
how to sow that seed.
Anything else.
And
all these techniques only work
if we are the
living laboratory for these techniques.  So if you do
n't try it and that's your experiments, you won't
know.
What I'm telling you is to do your own
experiments, because everyone already has
their own preconceived notions and even their own
very particular way of perceiving this
type of teaching.  So,
with the seeds you already have and
with your current
subjective vision, we could call it
that, you have to do your
experiments.  These are like maps, but
everyone has to make their own way
, right?
What I found from this question and
several other questions is that, who
is perceiving
the priest who is not happy?   It
complicates things a bit, but it's an
important question, isn't it?  Who is
noticing that the friend is
sick?  Who is perceiving that the country
is unhappy?  So, that's also an
important question to ask.  I'll leave you with
the question rather than the answer.
[Music]
Sorry here.
And at this moment in my life I have
many people around me who are
suffering separations,
marital crises,
[Music]
which I have already suffered, but luckily I was
able to recover.
And in the vast majority of cases, what's
happening to them is the economic aspect
that prevents them from separating or causes
a big fight.  And I don't really know
his first question, how,
why are they approaching me?
I just got ready and everything's coming back to me
.
um are having problems like economic
problems other the problem is that they
don't have money and because of that
they cannot split
or uh that they are fighting for the
finances and she part of her question is
why are they all coming to her and now
that's because she got like divorce and
now she's back with her husband now they
are all coming to
[Music] Maybe it's
good luck that you
're here.
Something I've noticed in our lives
is that people gravitate towards each other; they do
n't feel a
gravitational pull towards people they
feel can help them.
[Music]
The most important thing, the first thing is that
you have this opportunity.
to help all these people who are coming
to you for an answer.
And the second thing I want to tell you is what
Eric also talked about and what we
talked about at the beginning of this reading,
which is about this understanding, this
wisdom that is crucial, which is
understanding where the things that happen to me come from
.
Whether it's your own sickness or
your friend's sickness, or whether it's
your own crisis in your marriage or your
friend's crisis in your marriage, it means
there's a
heart
and
you're...
so if you see, for example, whether you're
seeing that you have those
problems, that you have that crisis or
that separation, or that your friends
are having them at this moment.  That
speaks of a seed, uh, I'm not quite right in
saying that it's in your heart and that it's kind of
expressing itself in the world, right?
Leave him on the floor
with his back straight.
Now they are going to close their eyes.
[Laughter]
Feel how your spine lengthens
and notice the slow breathing.
[Laughter]
And now imagine that you are
arriving from Starbucks, you have already chosen your
person and gone to have the coffee and
arrived at your house.  You're arriving
home, you
open the door, you take off your shoes,
you get comfortable,
you do what you always do at home
to relax.  Maybe you'll watch a little
TV, since he didn't give us permission at the
beginning of the talk.
You can also eat something.
And then you take a bath,
get comfortable, and choose your
favorite spot to lie down, like in
the photo.  Okay, so you eat and lie there and
relax
and think,
"What did I do today?"   I
went to the bar and talked to this person
about how they can find their passion in
life.
So, I'm helping this person
find their passion.
We are here to learn how to find
our passion in life.  How to do or
how to do what I do every day
with passion.
that my whole body vibrates, that
my heart sings when I
go about my daily life, when I carry out
my life.  So, you're lying there,
relaxed in your bed or your
favorite armchair, and you think about what you did and
you say, "I went to the cafe, you went to the
cafe, and you helped someone think about
their passion."  And that planted a seed
in your mind, a seed that will
blossom into
you finding your passion and
rejoicing in it.  Decs, "That's great,
I'm very smart. I did what Key
told her. Very good, I finally got up the nerve to call. I'm
very happy."  You say to yourself, you
tell yourself, "Very good, well done."  And you
rejoice.  You really feel in your
heart that you did something really good
and you keep thinking about it while lying in bed and you
see yourself in a time when
that seed blossoms
and you have passion.
Like the teachers who were up here,
they have passion inside their hearts.  And
then your friends see you and say,
"You're doing great. What did you do? Tell me your
secret."
Then you have the opportunity to
share this with them. Then
they learn and in turn teach, and it's
like—you see it in your mind. Yes, like
when the sun rises and the earth is
dark and it gradually illuminates until it
lights up the whole earth, just like
a virus that spreads throughout the
world, but this is a good virus, and it
keeps spreading, and more and more
people are helping each other.
So, with this small action
you took, a small seed you
planted, you're
watching your tree, your plant, grow
enormously,
and you feel happiness in your heart
because you realize—you're smart—
you realize what a good seed you planted. You
congratulate yourself, you hug yourself.
How happy I am!
Then you
rest your head on the pillow or
the cushion of the couch
and you start to fall asleep,
thinking about what you
did. You feel your enormous heart
vibrating,
and you feel in your  Heart, what
you did makes sense, it's real. It
works. I
can do it, I can do it. I
did it today. It's real. And you go to sleep
with a happy heart, remembering what
you did, like from a
tiny seed, you were able to give so much,
and you drift off to sleep with your heart
full of joy.
[Laughter]
And you open your eyes slowly
and you commit to having this
real meditation after your coffee. Yeah.